Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *Daf* is ס"ז *Samech Zayin*,
ס"ח *Samech Chet*?
ס"ח
*Samech Chet*. And we start with literally the last word on ס"ז
עמוד Amud ב' *Samech Zayin Amud Bet* and the discussion is whether
we know that a בעל קרי ba'al keri. *Baal Keri* we are
in a digression here because we talked about פסח pesach *Pesach* being
brought on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* which led us to a discussion about
פסח pesach *Pesach* being brought בטומאה betumah *bi-tumah*
which then had us looking both at the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* of
איש איש כי יהיה טמא tamei, לנפש *Ish Ish Ki Yiheyeh Tamei
La-nefesh* that if a person is טמא tamei לנפש *tamei la-nefesh* for
a soul, for corpse טומאה tumah *tumah*, they bring the פסח Pesach,
שני *Pesach Sheni* and the דרשה *derasha* was an individual but a
ציבור tzibbur *tzibur* would bring it on the פסח Pesach, ראשון *Pesach
Rishon*. And that then led to a discussion also of the different
levels of טומאה tumah. *tumah*.
One is טמא מת tmei meit *Tamei Meis* which we would think
is more severe, but actually the more severe ones were זב zav,
*Zav* and מצורע metzora *Metzora*, people whose טומאה *tumah* came from their
very body and to the טומאה יוצאת מגופו *tumah yotzei mi-gufo* and
that led to a three-way division of the degree to which you
had to be away from sent out of the camps, which translates
to distance from the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. That a טמא מת
tamei meit *Tamei Meis* has to be out of the מקדש mikdash.
*Mikdash* but he can be in מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah, *Machaneh Leviyah*
which is הר הבית Har HaBayit. *Har HaBayis*, Temple
Mount. A זב zav *Zav* has to be out of מחנה לוייה
machaneh leviyah, *Machaneh Leviyah* but he can be in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*
or מחנה ישראל Machaneh Yisrael? *Machaneh Israel* and a מצורע metzora *Metzora*
has to be even out of that. And the question is what
is the story of a בעל קרי ba'al keri *Baal Keri*? On
the one hand it comes out of his body, it's a similar,
it's out of a penile flow like a זב *Zav*. Is he
considered to be but it's only a one day טומאה *tumah*, which
camp is he part of? Is he part of זב *Zav* and
can't be on הר הבית Har HaBayit. *Har HaBayis* or he's like
טמא מת tamei meit. *Tamei Meis* and can be on הר הבית
Har HaBayit, *Har HaBayis*? Relevant today about going up to הר הבית
Har HaBayit. *Har HaBayis* when people are in certain states. Anyway, so
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* having there's the statement is that of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* that a בעל קרי ba'al keri *Baal
Keri* is like a זב *Zav* for this purpose, but now it
is being questioned.
So זב *Zav* and נידה *Niddah* are clearly aligned. Right. But בעל
קרי ba'al keri *Baal Keri* because it's only a one day
טומאה *tumah* is the question exactly. Right. טמא tamei. מת *Tamei Meis*
is only... I know, but the בעל קרי ba'al keri *Baal Keri*
has aspects of טומאה יוצאת מגופו *tumah yotzei mi-gufo*, so in that
way it is a similar to a זב *Zav* and a נידה
*Niddah* and so on, and on the other hand, he's more lenient
than them because it's one day and that's why we don't know
where to categorize him. So מיתיבי *Meisvei* says גמרא gemara *Gemara*, I'll
ask you on this, top of ס"ח עמוד א' A, *Samech Chet
Amud Aleph*. בועל נידה כטמא מת *Boel Niddah ke-Tamei Meis*. The end
of that ברייתא braisa *braisa* that said a בעל קרי ba'al keri,
*Baal Keri* was like a זב *Zav* which we said maybe didn't
mean the camps, maybe meant their level of טומאה *tumah*.
Here the end of that ברייתא braisa *braisa* says that a בועל
נידה *Boel Niddah*, a man who has sex with a נידה *niddah*,
is like a person who came in contact with a dead. So
למאי הלכתא *le-mai hilkheta*? For what הלכה halacha. *halacha*? אילימא לטומאה סתם
stam. *Ileima le-tumah stam* if you tell me that they have an
equal degree of טומאה *tumah*, האי טומאת שבעה כתיב ksiv, ביה והאי
טומאת שבעה כתיב ביה *hai tumas shiva kesiv bei v'hai tumas shiva
kesiv bei*, they each say they have a seven day טומאה *tumah*,
so the ברייתא braisa *braisa* wouldn't have to say that. אלא לאו
למחניה *Ela lav le-machaneh*, so it must be telling you for their
camps, that a בועל נידה *Boel Niddah* has the same can go
into מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah, *Machaneh Leviyah*, he has the same camp
as a somebody who came in contact with the dead, again it's
not a טומאה *tumah* that comes from his own body, it's contracted
from the outside, here from sex with a woman who is a
נידה *niddah*. And therefore it is the weakest of the טומאות *tumaos*
for this purpose and can be even in the inner camp, just
not in the
מקדש mikdash *Mikdash*. ומדסיפא למחניה *Umide-seifa le-machaneh* since that equation is speaking
about having the same camps, הוי רישא נמי למחניה *havei reisha nami
le-machaneh*, so the first part which said that a בעל קרי ba'al
keri? *Baal Keri* is like a זב *Zav* also refers to sharing
the same camp and means that a בעל קרי ba'al keri *Baal
Keri* has to be out of the Levite camp, out of מחנה
לוייה machaneh leviyah. *Machaneh Leviyah* off of הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har
HaBayis*.
Wait, wait, wait. You're saying the בועל נידה *Boel Niddah* is now
like the טמא tamei. מת *Tamei Meis*, he only needs to be
out of one camp? Right. But if he's a בועל נידה *Boel
Niddah*, he's also בעל קרי ba'al keri. *Baal Keri*.
That is a good question. Not necessarily, that's an excellent question, but
it could be a בועל נידה *Boel Niddah* without being a בעל
קרי ba'al keri *Baal Keri*. Right, so that we'd have to assume
that, but that's a very good point, that we'd have to assume
not that. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says מידי איריא *midi irya*?
What, is that a proof? הכא כדיתליה והכא כדיתליה *hacha k'de-islei v'hacha
k'de-islei*, each one is according to its own parameters, just because one
of them means a sharing the camp and that's the purpose of
the equation, is not necessarily what the other one means. All right,
let's see now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מיתיבי *Meisvei*, I'll ask you on this
assertion that a בעל קרי ba'al keri *Baal Keri* is like a
זב *Zav* and have to be off of הר הבית Har HaBayit,
*Har HaBayis*. מצורע metzora חמור מזב *Metzora chamur
mi-zav*. A מצורע *Metzora* is more strict than a זב *Zav*. וזב
חמור מטמא מת *V'zav chamur mi-tamei meis*. And a זב *Zav* is
more strict than a טמא מת *Tamei Meis*. Obviously this means for
what we've been talking about, how far which camps they have to
be sent out of. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says יצא בעל
קרי ba'al keri *yatzah Baal Keri*, so the ברייתא braisa *braisa* continues
to say the following: יצא בעל קרי ba'al keri. *yatzah Baal Keri*,
this excludes a בעל קרי *Baal Keri* שטמא מת חמור ממנו *she-tamei
meis chamur mi-menu*, that a טמא מת *Tamei Meis* is even more
strict than him. So what's excluding a בעל קרי *Baal Keri*? Somehow
he's excluded from this general decision. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
מאי יצא *mai yatzah*? What does it mean he's taken out or
he's excluded? לאו *Lav* would... not the way to read this ברייתא
baraita *braita* to be the following, יצא מכלל זב *yatza mikhlal zav*
meaning this division טמא מת *tmei meis*, זב *zav*, מצורע *metzora* excludes
a בעל קרי *baal keri*. A בעל קרי *baal keri* is not
to be included in the category of זב *zav*, although they both
have these emissions. Don't include him in the category of זב *zav*,
ובא לכלל טמא מת *u'va l'klal tmei meis*, he should be in
the lowest category. Why? דטמא מת חמור ממנו *detmei meis chamur mimenu*,
because even a טמא מת *tmei meis* is more strict, it's a
seven-day and this guy only a one-day. So you have a ברייתא
baraita, *braita* that says a בעל קרי *baal keri* is an exception.
Presumably it means it's an exception from the זב *zav* category because
it's even lower than a טמא מת *tmei meis*, and therefore does
not have to go any further away than in the camp that's
more outer than that of a טמא מת *tmei meis*. ומותר במחנה
לוייה leviyah; *u'mutar bemachaneh leviyah*, and he can even go into מחנה
לוייה machaneh leviyah *machaneh leviyah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא
*lo*, no, that's not necessarily how we had to read the ברייתא
Braisa, *braita*. Here's how you could read the ברייתא Braisa *braita*: יצא
ממחנה טמא מת *yatza mimachaneh tmei meis*, means a בעל קרי *baal
keri* is excluded, means he's excluded from the more lenient category.
It's telling you a בעל קרי *baal keri*'s an exception, but he's
an exception from what category? To what? So what would your assumption
have been? So the first reading is your assumption would have been
put him with a זב *zav* and the ברייתא Braisa *braita* say
no, he's an exception, he's so lenient he's an exception. This reading
is saying no, your assumption would have been put him with a
טמא מת *tmei meis*, he's very lenient, it's only one day, and
the ברייתא Braisa *braita*'s saying no no no he's an exception, he's
more strict. ונכנס למחנה זב *venichnas lemachaneh zav*, he has to be
treated just like a זב *zav*.
Something wrong with the logic I can't put my
finger on it.
To say somebody's an exception I think there's an underpinning assumption of
right yeah, assumption is what the rule is but we don't know.
ואף על גב *ve'af al gav*, and the way to read it
is not he's an exception because he's more lenient than a טמא
מת *tmei meis* and therefore he's in the more lenient category. He's
an exception regardless of the fact, meaning the reason he's an exception
is it's true he's more lenient than a טמא מת *tmei meis*,
ואף על גב דטמא מת חמור ממנו *ve'af al gav detmei meis
chamur mimenu*. It's true a טמא מת *tmei meis* is more strict
and he's nevertheless an exception to that way of categorizing it and
take him out of טמא מת *tmei meis* and put him with
a זב *zav*. ודטמא מת חמור ממנו *udtmei meis chamur mimenu* מותר
במחנה לוייה leviyah *mutar bemachaneh leviyah*. A טמא מת *tmei meis* is
allowed in מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah. *machaneh leviyah* and a בעל קרי
*baal keri* is even more lenient and nevertheless he's an exception to
that categorization and he gets put with a זב *zav*. So למאי
דדמי ליה מדמינן ליה *le'mai de'dami lei midamina lei*. We nevertheless put
him not with the level of severity hierarchy but with the more
qualitative
categorization. And conceptually he's more similar to a זב *zav*. So you
take him out of the category of טמא מת *tmei meis*, he's
an exception to that hierarchy and you put him with a זב
*zav* because he's more similar to a זב *zav*.
So how how you reading that למאי דדמי ליה מדמינן ליה *le'mai
de'dami lei midamina lei*?
We compare him to the category he's most comparable to, which means
comparable in terms of I would sort of say the characteristics, not
the severity. למאי דדמי ליה מדמינן ליה *le'mai de'dami lei midamina lei*.
So because the characteristics is more similar to that of a זב
*zav*, he's put in זב *zav* category even though he's in severity
he's very lenient. He's an exception to the rule of severity and
he gets put into the category of what he's similar to. Anyway
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not have a conclusion. It has
this debate of the story of a בעל קרי *baal keri* on
מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah. *machaneh leviyah*, which as I said is a
serious question about going on a הר הבית Har HaBayit, *Har Habayis*
tour. Even if you think you can avoid מקום המקדש mekom hamikdash.
*mekom hamikdash* for a well first of all a woman who's a
נידה *niddah* is definitely not allowed, that's certainly in the more strict
category. And for a man who's a בעל קרי *baal keri*, and
so you first of all the tour guides would have to say
you know based on if you know whatever happens the night before
the tour, either don't come on the tour or make sure to
go to the מקווה *mikvah* first thing in the morning. But even
if you go to the מקווה *mikvah* first thing in the morning,
there's another discussion of whether a טבול יום tevul yom *tvul yom*
of a בעל קרי *baal keri* has the same status as the
בעל קרי *baal keri*. So actually you know you should have a
few people always dropping off of some of these tours before they
go, but it doesn't happen so it's a real issue, it's a
halakhic question.
Does רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* have a position on this?
I don't remember, I'd have to check how רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* holds.
Okay and as I did say by the way, the one thing
I never understood which I don't the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not
discuss, I'm sure somebody must discuss it is if a בעל קרי
*baal keri*'s אסור assur *assur* מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah *machaneh leviyah*, I
don't understand how the כוהנים *kohanim* and the לויים *levi'im* in the
time of the משכן mishkan *mishkan* were able to sleep with their
wives. I mean they were able to but as soon as they
did they'd have to get up and go out to their friend's
house in מחנה ישראל machaneh yisrael. *machaneh yisrael* until they go to
the מקווה *mikvah* and whatever the next morning.
They're on shifts, they weren't there the whole year.
No no no and they weren't in the מקדש Mikdash *mikdash* but
in the מדבר *midbar* they were in the מחנה לוייה machaneh leviyah,
*machaneh leviyah*. They were in the camps that surrounded the משכן *mishkan*.
And if a בעל קרי *baal keri* can't be in that camp,
as soon as a man has a seminal emission either by himself
or with his wife, he has to get up and leave. Now
maybe you say that there was a מקווה *mikvah* so I don't
know where they had מקוואות *mikva'os* in the desert. They'd have to
go the nearest ocean or something.
באר של מרים *be'er shel miriam*, באר של מרים *be'er
shel miriam* both
go into the מדבר *midbar*.
Well okay, they were periodic, I don't know. Okay anyway, but even
if they went to the מקווה *mikvah* in the middle of the
night they'd have to be able to come back, it would depend
on whether the הלכה *halakha* of טבול יום *tvul yom* whether they
could have to still wait till the next day before coming home.
I really don't get it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, תני תנא tana קמיה ד- *tani tana kamei de-*. The
תנא tana taught in front of רב יצחק בר אבדימי. Rav Yitzchak
bar Avdimi. The תנא taught in front of רב יצחק בר אבדימי.
Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. Still with this issue of the degree of
camps that the טמאים tmei'im would have to leave from: ויצא מחוץ
למחנה. Veyatza michutz lamachaneh. Now this is literally, this is explicitly about
the בעל קרי. It says איש כי יהיה בו מקרה לילה. Ish
ki yiheyeh vo mikreh laylah. What is it? What's the whole
פסוק? pasuk איש אשר לא יהיה טהור מקרה לילה?
Ish asher lo yiheyeh tahor
mikreh laylah?
What? איש
אשר לא יהיה טהור מקרה לילה, Ish asher lo yiheyeh tahor mikreh
laylah, ויצא מחוץ למחנה, veyatza michutz lamachaneh, לא יבוא אל תוך המחנה.
lo yavo el toch hamachaneh. So somebody has some nighttime event, which
means he has a seminal emission. Here it says he goes out
of the camp, and this is exactly the question we're asking: out
of which camp, right, does the בעל קרי go out of? מחנה
שכינה? Machaneh Shechinah? What? Well, okay, does he also, but that was
putting him in the most strict thing, that he needn't even be
out of מחנה machaneh ישראל? Israel, Nobody's suggesting that. So let's take
a look at what this ברייתא Braisa says. ויצא מחוץ למחנה, Veyatza
michutz lamachaneh, this בעל קרי goes out of the camp, זו מחנה
שכינה, zo machaneh shechinah, out of the camp of the שכינה, shechinah,
meaning he can't be in the משכן area or in the מקדש.
Mikdash לא יבוא אל תוך המחנה, Lo yavo el toch hamachaneh, the
repetition, now don't come into the camp, means there's yet another camp
you can't go into. Thank you. זו מחנה לוייה, zo machaneh leviyah,
he can't go into מחנה machanehs לוייה, so according to this ברייתא
Braisa he can't even, again, a בעל קרי has to be outside
of מחנה machanehs לוייה, outside of הר הבית. Har HaBayit מכאן לבעל
קרי שיצא חוץ לשתי מחנות. Mikan leva'al keri sheyatza chutz lishtei machanot.
So this ברייתא Braisa says he goes out of two camps, so
that's a ברייתא Braisa, that supports רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, so when this תנא said it to רב יצחק
בר אבדימי, Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, רב יצחק בר אבדימי Rav Yitzchak
bar Avdimi said back to him: אכתי לא עיילתיה אפקתיה? Akti lo
ayiltei apiktei? You haven't even brought him in, you're going to take
him out? Meaning, what does that mean? It's actually a more comprehensible
other version: לשנא אחרינא אכתי לא אפקתיה עיילתיה, lishna acharina akti lo
apiktei ayiltei, he hasn't yet gone out and you're bringing him in?
Meaning, if you say go out of מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, your
next sentence can't be: and don't come into מחנה machaneh לוייה, right?
Because he only got out of מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, so don't
come into מחנה שכינה. machaneh shechinah. What you're not allowed to come
into is a place you've already been ejected from. So you cannot
read it, you know, don't get out of מחנה שכינה machaneh shechinah
and I don't want to see you coming into מחנה לוייה. Then
you first have to kick him out of מחנה לוייה before you
tell him not to come in.
Why, when you say leave the מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, it means
go all the way?
Okay, but
then it doesn't just mean leave מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, it means
leave מחנה לוייה.
Okay, but the point is most people presumably spoke into local congregations.
So why can't you read it like I was saying, go out
of whatever camp you're in?
So that's essentially what he's asking. But you can't read it the
way you wanted it read. You wanted it to read leave מחנה
שכינה machaneh shechinah only, then the next statement is not: don't come
into מחנה לוייה.
Okay, so
let's see what his answer is. אלא אימא, Ela eima, here's how
you have to read it: מחוץ למחנה, michutz lamachaneh, get out of
a camp, זו מחנה לוייה, zo machaneh leviyah, get out of לוייה;
לא יבוא אל תוך המחנה, lo yavo el toch hamachaneh, don't come
into the camp, זו מחנה שכינה. zo machaneh shechinah. Meaning, then
that then even makes sense because the לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, which
is more severe, you only transgress when you get even more inner.
So get out of מחנה לוייה and don't come into מחנה שכינה.
machaneh shechinah. So if you stay in מחנה לוייה, you transgress the
עשה, asseh, but if you go so far to go into מחנה
שכינה, machaneh shechinah, then you're even transgressing the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
How do you know it doesn't mean just the camp you're in?
Because the גמרא Gemara has a vested interest not to read it
that way. The גמרא Gemara understands based on everything we said yesterday
that only a מצורע is out of מחנה ישראל. Yisrael So מתקיף
לה רבינא, matkif lah Ravina, so רבינא Ravina said: אימא אידי ואידי
למחנה שכינה. eima idi ve'idi lemachaneh shechinah. You know, let's read this
פסוק pasuk? minimally. Get out of the camp, don't come into the
camp, means the same camp, and we'll read it the most minimalist
way, meaning מחנה שכינה. machaneh shechinah. ולעבור עליו בעשה ולא תעשה, v'la'avor
alav b'asseh v'lo ta'aseh, and the reason you need two פסוקים psukim
is to tell me it's doubly prohibited, there's a positive and negative
מצווה mitzvah that applies to this. But not that it's two separate
camps, it's all talking about one camp, and we'll take the תפסת
מרובה לא תפסת tafasta merubah lo tafasta approach and we'll say the
most minimalist read is just מחנה שכינה. machaneh shechinah. There's no repetition
here, the reason it repeated it was to say there's both a
positive and a negative commandment.
In ירושלים, Yerushalayim the מחנה שכינה machaneh shechinah is the מקדש Mikdash.
itself, the precincts, and לוייה is anywhere הר הבית.
Har HaBayit Anywhere הר הבית, Har HaBayit. including all the way up
to עזרת ישראל. ezrat yisrael. Even עזרת נשים ezrat nashim has the
status of הר הבית. Har HaBayit, So that's why again on these
tours, you know, since a טמא מת is only אסור assur on
in
מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechinah, they feel as long as they know they're
not going into the עזרה azarah area, they feel confident they're avoiding
the עזרה azarah area, they're allowed, you know, they'll take people up.
Do you think the bottom of הר הבית Har HaBayit is considered
like ירושלים Yerushalayim, then?
No, from the beginning of the wall of the inside of the
wall around הר הבית, Har HaBayit, all the
way, including everything except where the עזרה azarah begins, עזרת ישראל ezrat
yisrael begins. By the way, if you want to know some real
חומרות, chumros, I was telling you about questions about having somebody who's
a בעל קרי go up, but there are some people that won't
stick their hand— into the cracks in the כותל. Kotel. Why? To
put the notes in. Well, probably these same people would be against
putting the notes in for a lot of other reasons, but one
of the reasons that they don't do it is, if you're a
בעל קרי, you're אסור assur on הר הבית, Har HaBayit right, assuming
according to this גמרא, Gemara and there's another discuss- the same way
there's a discussion what if you've gone to the מקוה, mikvah, what
if you're- what if you're, you know, a טבול יום of a
בעל קרי? There's also discussion, what's the halakhic status of ביאה במקצת,
bi'ah bemiktzat, if only part of your body went in? And then
there's another question, where does הר הבית begin, on the inside of
the- on the inner sort of plane of the wall or the
outer plane of the wall? So if you think הר הבית begins
on the outer plane of the wall, and you're afraid of ביאה
במקצת, bi'ah bemiktzat, so even if your- the tip of your finger
goes- crosses the line, that's considered a prohibition. So therefore they won't
even put their fingers into the cracks of הר הבית. No, because
that's- let's- let's not go in yet, it's not passing the line.
Yes, although רבנו- Rabbenu the Rabbi of the כותל Kotel wrote a
תשובה teshuvah that women who are נדות niddot are not permitted to
touch the כותל. Kotel.
Oh, from this reason? He published it! Pshhh! Yes. That's crazy. Nobody's
ever said that.
Yeah, he has, he's written it and it's in the book of
the Western Wall Heritage Fund.
Oh my God. I- I-
I'd be interested looking at it.
I can't see how then-
unless he makes it a גזירה, gezerah, you'll pass- you'll come to...
oh, some- some Rabbi's
make up stuff.
Alright, so... No, he might be basing it
on this, what you just said.
Right. Oh, some combination of these things.
...on the outside of the...
Yeah, but I've never heard anybody say that you can't even on
the outside. But he did. Alright. Alright, so anyway, so גמרא Gemara
says like this, maybe it's an עשה asei and a לא תעשה
lo ta'asei and it's still just limited to מחנה שכינה. Machaneh Shekhinah.
So no, אם כן לימא קרא, im ken leima kra, ויצא אל
מחוץ למחנה ולא יבוא אל תוך. veyeitzei el michutz lamachaneh velo yavo
el toch. Just- why did it- why did it say מחנה twice?
Just say 'get out of the camp and don't come inside' ולא
יבוא אל תוכה velo yavo el tokhah I guess. המחנה למה לי?
Ha-machaneh lamma li? Why did it repeat the word המחנה? ha-machaneh? שמע
מינה אתניה למחנה אחרת, Shema mina itneih le-machaneh acherit, to tell me
that there are two מחנה that are off limits.
היא היא המחנה.
Hee hee ha-machaneh. Yeah. Or just the repetition, that there's two מחנה
that are off limits. So you're right, based on the grammar we
can't say that the לא תעשה lo ta'asei applies to the- to
the outer one, but we can say the לא תעשה lo ta'asei
applies to the inner one, the מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shekhinah, and the
עשה asei to the outer one, so at least a בעל קרי
would be אסור assur in מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, at least by
an עשה. asei. So I want to make it clear by the
way, the only חיוב כרת chiyuv karet is when somebody actually goes
with טמא, whether טמא מת or any טומאה onto- into מחנה שכינה,
Machaneh Shekhinah, into the area of the עזרה. Azarah. That's the חיוב
כרת chiyuv karet of a טמא entering into מקום המקדש. Makom Hamikdash,
All of these other things, about a מצורע going into
ירושלים, Yerushalayim. according to תוספות Tosafot that's just an עשה, asei, or
according to another way of reading the גמרא Gemara it's a לא
תעשה lo ta'asei but it's connected to an עשה. asei. And according
to a זב, so that's number one, מצורע going into ירושלים. A
זב going up to הר הבית,
that's a לא תעשה lo ta'asei without כרת. karet. And now our
question is a בעל קרי. א, is a בעל קרי prohibited on
הר הבית or not? That's debated. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, says he
is prohibited, this ברייתא Braisa supported רבי Rabbi יוחנן, but the גמרא
Gemara, was questioning it, maybe he's like a טמא מת. Even if
a בעל קרי is prohibited on הר הבית, how prohibited is he?
First it seems like he was prohibited with a לא תעשה. lo
ta'asei. Again, no כרת. karet. And then according to this ברייתא, Braisa.
only prohibited with an עשה. asei. Okay, so whatever the prohibition of
a בעל קרי on הר הבית is, which itself is debated, it
certainly is not כרת karet and it might not even be a
לא תעשה, lo ta'asei, according to this it might only be an
עשה. asei. Nevertheless, it doesn't mean that you don't have to attend
to it, so again, the issue with how those tours are- are
handled in- in the old city. Now, what's the עשה?
asei? What's the פסוק? pasuk ויצא אל מחוץ למחנה. Veyeitzei el michutz
lamachaneh.
So that might refer to מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. Okay, that's explicitly
ויצא אל מחוץ למחנה,
veyeitzei
el
michutz lamachaneh, that's explicitly a בעל קרי.
Right. And on the לא תעשה lo ta'asei you would get מלקות?
malkot?
Yeah, presumably.
For the עשה asei you wouldn't. Right.
So now, now we are able to move on from this division
of the camps of טומאה. By the way, this is all a
precursor to much more discussion we're gonna have later on about the-
about the reality of a פסח that is brought when the ציבור
tzibbur is טמא. Now we were just laying the groundwork of where
we know it from the פסוקים pesukim that a פסח can be
brought בטומאה if the ציבור is טמא. The actual discussion of that
comes later. But now we go back to the משנה Mishnah about
שבת Shabbat. and what can be done on שבת. Shabbat So one
of the things that can be done on שבת Shabbat is the-
the
cleansing of the- intestines from the- fecal matter, you know, and that
you're allowed to do even on שבת Shabbat and then you have
to burn it because, you know, otherwise they would- they would spoil,
they would stink and spoil. But you're not allowed to actually rinse
them out, but you're allowed to cleanse them. So the גמרא Gemara
wants to know, what's the line between cleansing and rinsing? So let's
take a look. ומיחוי קרביים. Umikhu'ach kreivah. מאי מיחוי קרביים? Mai mikhu'ach
kreivah? What does this mean, the sort of cleansing of the- of
the- intestines? רב הונא אמר שמנקבין בסכין, Rav Huna amar shemenakvim besakin,
that you make a hole with a knife into it like... into
the, you know, intestines in particular, and through that hole you squeeze
out the various like, you know, digested food. חייא בר
רב אמר Hiyya bar Rav amar שירקא דמי עייא דנפקא
אגב דוחקא דסכינא, shirka damei aya d'nafka agav duchka d'sakina, the like
sort of liquids of the intestines that come out by the pressure
of the knife. So it sounds like according to him, it's not
like you would actually, you know, cut it, but you would sort
of use, I don't know why you have to use a knife,
but you'd push on it, you know, in order to push out
all of the whatever the you know fecal matter that is in
there, the digested food.
Now he's talking about like a, what's it called, שחיטה shechita or
whatever?
Yes, it's an interesting question how absorbed is it or is it
just contained in it like something would be contained in a balloon
or something? You know, I don't know, but
anyway, you're allowed to do things that are צורך הקרבה, tzorch hakrava,
and this is צורך הקרבה tzorch hakrava because you need to do
this in order to be מקריב makriv the אימורין. emurim.
And you can't just plunk it in water, just let it sit
there?
Yeah, apparently this was, it's funny, you know, you would think rinsing
out is the least of your problems, right? What's the big deal
rinsing something out? So it really is strange exactly why this is
allowed and דווקא davka the rinsing is not.
I imagine you have something like a tube, right? filled with stuff
and you put the knife down this way, and you're pulling it
and the stuff comes...
Right, that's the way I do matter, it's like you sort of...
I would imagine like more like you squeeze... Right, you sort of
you know do it like this until you get it out.
It would have to be that you did that way, otherwise you
put this object down the knife and you're pulling it down...
Or you're going like this with a knife to squeeze it out,
right. But again, I don't know why that's seen as more acceptable
than the rinsing unless the point is that you'd have to do
both and since that suffices you can't also do the rinsing after
that. But the rinsing presumably would not have done it by itself.
Okay, so אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, מאי טעמא mai ta'ama
דחייא בר רב? d'Chiyya bar Rav? What's the reason of חייא בר
רב? Hiyya bar Rav? That speaks about like the pressure of a
knife? דכתיב וחרבות מחים
גרים יאכלו. D'ketiv v'charvot mechim gerim yocheilu. And וחרבות מחים, v'charvot mechim,
which I looked at the standard English translation, which I don't even
remember anymore, but it was not clear to me how the standard
English translation I was getting from, I forget which it was I
was looking at, the JPS תנ"ך Tanakh or something, connected to those
words. Anyway, וחרבות מחים v'charvot mechim the strangers will... So what does
that mean? מאי משמע? mai mashma? כמתרגם רב יוסף, Ke-metargem Rav Yosef,
ונכסי דרשיעיא צדיקיא יחסנון. u-nichsei d'rasha'aya tzadika ya-achasnun. The wealth of the
property of the wicked
the righteous will inherit. So גרים gerim are the righteous. So רש"י
Rashi actually says because it's like עם ישראל Am Yisrael is sort
of like sojourners in this world, like you know they're constantly maybe
being displaced or something. Anyway, somehow גרים gerim identifies כלל ישראל, Klal
Yisrael, identifies the righteous. And וחרבות מחים v'charvot mechim is the חרב,
cherev, the sword, and the מחים mechim is like מיחוי, michui, so
it's the disgusting stuff, you know. So that's what it, so that's
the way רש"י Rashi understands it. The stuff that gets pushed out
by the sword, this disgusting stuff, you know. So somehow I don't
know how that means wealth, but anyway it means רשעים, resha'im, the
stuff of רשעים, resha'im, that will be inherited by the righteous. So
now that we're talking about that, we look at the beginning of
the פסוק pasuk, in ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, which is also
not so clear what it means. ורעו כבשים כדברם. V'ra'u kvassim k'dabram.
This is before it said
וחרבות מחים גרים יאכלו. v'charvot mechim gerim yocheilu. The sheep, the flock,
will graze as has been spoken, as has been spoken about them,
or as they
spoke. Oh, גרים? garim? So the גמרא Gemara was reading it גרים,
gerim, but I might be... that I assumed that that has the
right נקודות, nekudot, or at least the traditional נקודות nekudot for them.
Do we have a תנ"ך Tanakh there? Yeah, what's that big... what
is that...
ישעיהו ה, Yeshayahu Heh, it's towards the end of
ה, Heh, I
think.
יז? Yud Zayin? ורעו כבשים כדברם וחרבות מחים גרים יאכלו. V'ra'u kvassim
k'dabram v'charvot mechim garim yocheilu. You're right, גרים יאכלו. garim yocheilu. So
רש"י Rashi says, צדיקים כדברם גרים הצדיקים שהן כגרים יאכלו בתי
רשעים שהן שמנים,
Tzadikim k'dabram garim hatzadikim shehein k'gerim
yocheilu batay resha'im shehein shmanim, רש"י Rashi says. So that's שמנים. shmanim.
וחרבות מחים, v'charvot mechim, מחים mechim is like fatty, oh, I think,
anyway. I don't know what this means. I don't know. Anyway, moving
on. Okay.
So what does that mean? אמר נחמן בר ירמיה אמר רב, Amar
Nachman bar Yirmeya Amar Rav, כמדובר בם, k'medubar bam, like has been
spoken about them. What does that mean? מאי כמדובר בם? mai k'medubar
bam? What has been spoken about them? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, וחרבות
מחים גרים יאכלו. v'charvot mechim garim yocheilu. So here's what's going to
happen to the כבשים, kvassim, the flock, which is ישראל, they will
get as has been spoken to them, which is the second half
of the פסוק, pasuk they'll inherit the wealth of the רשעים. resha'im.
אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, בשלמא... bishlama... כתיב חורבות *charvot* if
it had no ו *vav*, just חורבות *charvot* כדקאמרת *kedekamart*, then you
could say this, the second half of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
the end of the first half. השתא דכתיב d'chtiv, וחורבות *hashata dechetiv
vecharvot*, and the חורבות *charvot*, it's not in the, it's not a,
the ending of the thought, it's a new point. מילתא חדתא היא
דקאמר *milta chadta hi deka'amar*, the second half of the פסוק pasuk?
*pasuk* is a different point. So the first half you have to
say something else. אלא אמר רבא Rava כדרב חננאל *ela amar Rava
kederav Chananel*. The first half means like רב חננאל אמר רב *Rav
Chananel amar Rav*. דאמר רב חננאל אמר רב *de'amar Rav Chananel amar
Rav*, עתידין צדיקים tzaddikim שיחיו את המתים *atidin tzadikim sheyichyu et hametim*.
So in the end, in the world to come, when the times
of משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*, it's not only will there be תחיית המתים
techiyat ha-metim. *tchiyat hametim*, which will come from God, that power will
be given to the צדיקים tzaddikim *tzadikim*. The righteous people will do
תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim, *tchiyat hametim*. I'm not sure if they're the
ones that are going to do תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim *tchiyat hametim*
for the whole world or they'll just have that power. Okay. כתיב
הכא ורעו כבשים כדברם *ketiv hacha vera'u kvassim kidevram*, the sheep will
graze as has been spoken about them, וכתיב u-chtiv, התם *uchetiv hatam*
ירעו בשן וגלעד כימי עולם *yir'u Bashan vegilad kimei olam*, כימי עולם
*kimei olam*,
that the בשן *Bashan* and גלעד *Gilad* will graze as in the
days of old. So there's a connection ורעו *vera'u* and ירעו *yir'u*.
Now let's see what we're going to do with the words בשן
*Bashan* and גלעד *Gilad*. So what's בשן *Bashan*? And like they used
to be able to do, כימי עולם *kimei olam*, like in the
times of old. So what is בשן *Bashan* and גלעד *Gilad*? בשן
זה אלישע *Bashan ze Elisha*. So בשן *Bashan* is אלישע *Elisha*, right?
There are two people in תנ"ך *Tanakh* that did a תחיית המתים
techiyat ha-metim *tchiyat hametim*, אלישע *Elisha* and אליהו *Eliyahu*. So בשן זה
אלישע *Bashan ze Elisha*, הבא מן הבשן *haba min habashan*, he came
from the area of the
בשן *Bashan*, שנאמר *shene'emar*, ויעני ושפט בבשן *vaya'ani veshafat babashan*. I'm sorry,
I was right the first time. He came from the locale of
בשן *Bashan* because it says these two people יעני ושפט *Ya'ani veshafat*
were in בשן *Bashan*. וכתיב *uchetiv*, and אלישע *Elisha* is בן שפט
*ben Shafat*, אשר יצק מים על ידי אליהו *asher yatzak mayim al
yedei Eliyahu*. Here's אלישע בן שפט *Elisha ben Shafat* who actually poured
the water, was the attendant of אליהו *Eliyahu*. So בשן *Bashan* refers
to אלישע *Elisha* who came from שפט *Shafat* who was from בשן
*Bashan*. גלעד זה אליהו *Gilad ze Eliyahu*, and גלעד *Gilad* is אליהו
*Eliyahu*, שנאמר ויאמר אליהו התשבי מתושבי גלעד *shene'emar vayomer Eliyahu hatishbi mitoshavai
Gilad*, that's right. So therefore, they will graze somehow means they will
have the power as they did of old, as they did in
the olden times when the צדיקים tzaddikim, *tzadikim* had the power to
do תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim *tchiyat hametim*.
And it's not just then.
And it's not just them.
I'm reading it that way. Right. These are the צדיקים tzaddikim *tzadikim*,
not all צדיקים tzaddikim *tzadikim*.
No, well, because they'll be brought back to life, so they'll have...
I don't know, it says, yeah...
I don't think so.
It seems like they will, you know, lead their sheep, they will...
to be... רועה *ro'eh*. Okay. Anyway. עתידין צדיקים tzaddikim שיחיו
את המתים *atidin
tzadikim
sheyichyu et hametim*.
Right. These צדיקים tzaddikim *tzadikim*, these two guys. Right.
That's what I said, שיחיו מתים *sheyichyu metim*. It's an active thing.
They will bring back...
right, they will do the תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim *tchiyat
hametim* that they're, that they're attending to. To be... ירעו כבשים *yir'u
kvassim*.
I don't know the grammar. How would you say to graze, ירעו
כבשים *yir'u kvassim* means to shepherd sheep or the sheep will graze?
ירעו בשן וגלעד *yir'u Bashan vegilad*. אליהו *Eliyahu*
and אלישע *Elisha* will be the...
they will shepherd, בשן *Bashan* and גלעד *Gilad* will ירעו *yir'u*,
they will shepherd their sheep.
Well, let's take a look, because I think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
very, really understands this to be all צדיקים tzaddikim *tzadikim*. Let's take
a look. So אמר רבי שמואל Shmuel בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן
*amar Rabi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabi Yonatan*, עתידין צדיקים שיחיו מתים
*atidin tzadikim sheyichyu metim*. The צדיקים *tzadikim* in the end will be
able to resurrect the dead, שנאמר *shene'emar*, עוד ישבו זקנים וזקנות ברחובות
ירושלים *od yeshvu zkenim uzkenot
birchovot Yerushalayim*, elder men and women will sit in the streets of
Jerusalem, ואיש משענתו בידו *ve'ish mishanto beyado*, and each person will have
his staff in his hand, מרוב ימים *merov yamim*, they'll be so
old that everybody will be walking around with these staffs because, you
know, that you only use in your old age. Everybody will live
to a nice long old age. So that's the simple sense of
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. וכתיב *uchetiv*, but what do we know about
a משענת *mishanot*? We know that that staff has some power by
תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim, *tchiyat hametim*. ושמת משענתי על פני הנער *veshamta
mishanti al pnei hana'ar*, אלישע *Elisha* says put my staff, my leaning
staff on the lad, and that brings him back to life. So
therefore, since it says that the elders will sit and they, each
person will have a staff, so it's not just אלישע *Elisha* and
אליהו *Eliyahu*, every person will have the ability, every צדיק tzaddik *tzadik*
or every זקן *zaken* and זקנה *zkenah* maybe will have the ability
to do תחיית המתים techiyat ha-metim, *tchiyat hametim*.
It doesn't call them צדיקים *tzadikim*.
Well, it calls them זקנים *zkenim*, I know.
So somehow the first מימרא *meimra* was just the two.
Now, I don't think the first... I disagree, I think the first
מימרא *meimra* was saying all of them will have, בגזירה שווה *begezeira
shava*, everybody will have the power that was had by... that's the
way... I think this was already in the first מימרא *meimra*. Anyway.
עולא רמי *Ulla rami*, עולא *Ulla* showed a contradiction. כתיב *ketiv*, the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says, בלע המות לנצח *bila hamavet lanetzach*, death will
cease forever in the future time, there'll no longer be any death.
וכתיב *uchetiv*, and the other verse says, כי הנער בן מאה שנה
ימות *ki hana'ar ben me'ah shanah yamut*, that a lad of a
hundred years will die, meaning a young death will be a hundred,
but there will still be death. Okay, so what's the story, will
there be death or won't there be death? לא קשיא lo kashya,
*la kashya*, it's
not difficult. כאן בישראל כאן בעובדי כוכבים *kan beYisrael kan
be'ovdei kochavim*. So okay, so the Jews will live forever and the
non-Jews will live a very long life. So the גמרא Gemara, says,
ועובדי כוכבים ונכרים מאי בעו התם? v'ovdei chochavim v'nochrim mai ba'u hatam?
I don't understand, what are the non-Jews doing in the world to
come? Well, who's going to serve the Jews? Oh, so that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara is not enough to
have this division, it doesn't think the non-Jews are there at all.
So the גמרא Gemara says, דכתיב, d'chtiv, no, they are doing something
there. Because it says, as Michael... ועמדו זרים ורעו צאנכם, v'amdu zarim
v'rau tzonchem, and the foreigners will get up and they will shepherd
your sheep. ובני נכר איכריכם וכרמיכם, u-vnei nechar ikareichem v'charmeichem, and sons
of the foreigners will be your, you know, will be your farmers
and tend to your vineyards. So therefore, but there will be this
difference that everybody will live very long, but ישראל forever.
Maybe the foreigners serving you will live long?
I don't know. I don't know what to say. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, ורמי רב חסדא. v'rami Rav Chisda. Now maybe that's
why you need the dead to do... the צדיקים to do תחיית
המתים. techiyat ha-metim, Meaning, I'm only partly joking here. When the גמרא
Gemara says the צדיקים do תחיית המתים, techiyat ha-metim is it basically
saying it's not going to come from God? The event that we
call תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim, will come from, you know, God will
empower the צדיקים, the צדיקים will do it. I mean, that's a
pretty radical idea thinking about the whole concept of משיח. Mashiach In
a way it could be very empowering in the sense that it's
sort of saying in the end even the תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim.
as it were is going to come from us. You know, don't
wait for everything to come from God. It could also just be
the idea of the power that צדיקים will have and sort of
expressed in very, you know,
extreme terms about to hold that up as, you know, as the...
that's when the צדיקים will get their true reward and people will
see their true power, they'll be able to do that. But again,
I don't know if it means, I don't know if it means
that the event that we call תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim, is going
to come from them or no. Maybe after תחיית המתים people will
die, you know, even after תחיית המתים, doesn't mean there'll be no
death. And then afterwards, from that point on, if you need somebody
brought back to brought back to life, you go see a צדיק
and they'll bring them back to life for you.
So, if the pagans are farming in... yeah, exactly. So I guess
people are eating, I suppose.
Yeah, that's also true. Exactly. So we'll see another difference in a
minute that the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with, what exactly
that future time will look like.
Perhaps it's a contrast to the previous discussion about how things are
not... even your bodily functions are under your control, your access to
God is not under your control.
Oh, that's a nice point. In contrast to that... That's very nice.
The whole concept about right, about being distant from the מקדש Mikdash,
and here even life and death becomes under your control. It's beautiful,
very nice. Okay, ורמי רב חסדא, v'rami Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav
Chisda shows a contradiction. דכתיב, one פסוק pasuk says, וחפרה הלבנה
ובושה החמה, v'chafra ha-levana u-vosha ha-chama, that the moon will be embarrassed
and the sun will be ashamed because the light of God will
be so great in the future, you know, that even the luminaries
will have no light to offer. וכתיב, the other verse says, והיה
אור הלבנה כאור החמה, v'haya or ha-levana k'or ha-chama, so the moon
will be as powerful as the sun. ואור החמה יהיה שבעתים כאור
שבעת הימים, v'or ha-chama yiheyeh shivtayim k'or shivat ha-yamim, and the sun
will be seven times, רש"י Rashi says 49 times as powerful as
the light of the seven days of בראשית. Bereishit. So רש"י Rashi
says 49 power times as powerful as all seven days combined, which
is like 350 times. Anyway. So these luminaries will be much more
powerful. They won't be outshone by the light of God, which is
the other verse.
Compared to how they are now.
All right. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, it's not difficult.
כאן לעולם הבא כאן לימות המשיח. kan l'Olam HaBa kan l'Yemot HaMashiach.
There's a difference between Messianic times and the עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
Messianic times will be miraculous, but there will still be a normal
type of a life. Meaning this is like what דב Dov said
before, you know, maybe there'll be a תחיית המתים, but people will
still eat and people will still maybe die, at least whatever the
division that the גמרא Gemara sets, that's Messianic times. But then the
time after Messianic times is עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
Now it's important to note this. If you tell a normal person
עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, what do they think about? They think about
oh, the world of souls where you go to after you die.
A lot of that re-emphasis or reorientation happened by the רמב"ם Rambam
to emphasize the sort of eternal life of the soul, but not
some... but de-emphasizing a miraculous life in this planet. But in the
simple גמרא, Gemara עולם הבא Olam HaBa is the world that is
going to exist in the future in this... on this planet. So
first you have this world, then you have the Messianic times, and
then you have the future utopia which will exist after Messianic times
and that's the עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. For example, right, for example,
the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin says, the משנה Mishna in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin says if somebody doesn't believe in תחיית המתים, they don't get
עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. And the גמרא says why not? Says well,
if you don't believe in it, you're not going to get it.
So the גמרא clearly links תחיית המתים with the period that follows
and the עולם הבא Olam HaBa that follows. So according to this
גמרא, right, in the time of משיח Mashiach. the luminaries will be
so bright, but in the time after that, that'll be complete utopia
and there it'll only be God shining. present. Okay, so that also
gets a little bit to Dov's question of whether people will be
eating and how much there will be real bodily sort of types
of functions. Now the גמרא says ולשמואל דאמר ule'Shmuel d'amar
according to שמואל Shmuel that doesn't believe in some miraculous messianic times,
maybe a miraculous עולם הבא Olam Haba yes, but not a miraculous
messianic times. He believes that in messianic times it will only be
the only difference is that we won't be under the subjugation of
non-Jews. So מאי איכא למימר mai ika lemeimar you can't say that
the brightness of the luminaries is for messianic times, because for him
that's a normal
it's a natural period in history.
So the
גמרא says אידי ואידי לעולם הבא. idi ve'idi l'Olam Haba. Okay, you're
right, but at least he still believes in an עולם הבא. Olam
Haba. So both of these verses are in the future true utopian
world. ולא קשיא, v'lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן במחנה שכינה כאן
במחנה צדיקים kan bemachaneh Shechinah kan bemachaneh tzaddikim talking about tying back
to the earlier discussion, right, which מחנה are you in? So if
you're right there in מחנה שכינה, machaneh Shechinah, which I don't know
had a technical הלכתי halachic meaning of like the עזרה azarah in
the מקום המקדש, you're right there in God's presence, then the sun
and the moon are embarrassed. Their light is meaningless in the presence
of God's presence. But if you're one step out, you're in the
camp where the צדיקים are but not right there with God, the
צדיקים who are going to do תחיית המתים, anyway there the brightness
of the luminaries will be so great.
שמואל Shmuel, did not believe in ימות המשיח? Yemos Hamashiach?
He believed in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, but not in a miraculous
ימות המשיח. Yemos Hamashiach. I'll say something about that in a minute.
Let's just get, yeah, not in a miraculous ימות המשיח. Yemos Hamashiach.
רבא רמי. Rava rami. רבא showed a contradiction. I'll say something in
a second. Let's get to the end of the page. כתיב, the
פסוק says
אני אמית ואחיה, ani amis va'achayeh, I will bring death and I
will bring life, and I give life. וכתיב מחצתי ואני ארפא, u'chsiv
machatzti va'ani erpa, I have wounded and I will heal. השתא חיויי
מחיי מרפא לא כל שכן? hashta chayuyei mechayeh marpei lo kol sheken?
If you already told me that you can bring back to life
or you can give life, of course you can heal. So what's
the point
of
the anti-climactic second half of the פסוק? אלא אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא,
ela amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, God is saying מה שאני ממית אני
מחיה. ma she'ani memis ani mechayeh. It's not that I will bring,
I cause death and I bring new life. No, the very thing
that I have caused to die, I will give life to that
thing that I have made
die. I will
resuscitate,
resuscitate is a better word than resuscitate. Anyway, someone wanted to use
the word revivify. Oh my
god. Anyway, okay. I will resurrect the dead, okay? The very same
person that I have been ממית memis I will be מחיה. mechayeh.
כמו, kemo, just like the end of the פסוק means, שמחצתי ואני
ארפא, shemachatzti va'ani erpa, when it says I will wound and heal,
heal means I'll heal what I wound. So here when it says
I will bring death and bring life, it means I'll bring life
to the one to whom I have brought death. So it means
the resurrection of the dead. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. אני אמית ואחיה.
ani amis va'achayeh. יכול מיתה באחד וחיים באחד? yachol misah b'echad ve'chayim
b'echad? Maybe it means I'll make one person die and bring a
new life to another person, כדרך שהעולם נוהג, kederech she'ha'olam noheg, like
nature works. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so the end of the verse
says מחצתי ואני ארפא. machatzti va'ani erpa. I will cause wounding and
I will heal. מה מכה ורפואה באחד, mah makah u'refuah b'echad, in
the same way the end of the פסוק means with one person,
the healing occurs to the person to whom the wound occurred, אף
מיתה וחיים באחד, af misah ve'chayim b'echad, so the beginning of the
פסוק means the life will be brought to the person to whom
the death occurred. מכאן תשובה לאומרים אין תחיית המתים מן התורה, mikan
teshuvah la'omrim ein techiyas hameisim min haTorah, and this is a response
to those that say that there's no basis of the resurrection in
the תורה, Torah, because it is מחצתי ואני machatzti va'ani because it's
ממית אני ואחיה memis ani va'achayeh in the same person. דבר אחר,
davar acher, another way of reading it. בתחילה מה שאני ממית אני
מחיה. betechilah mah she'ani memis ani mechayeh. First, the people I cause
to die I'll bring to life. First there'll be a תחיית המתים.
והדר, ve'hadar, after the תחיית המתים, מה שמחצתי ואני ארפא. mah shemachatzti
va'ani erpa. Everybody that gets resurrected and has wounds and somebody is
missing an arm and the other person has a missing leg, after,
first I'll resurrect them and then I'll heal their wounds. Okay, and
that will be in the messianic times. That's an interesting end to
this discussion, maybe after all the discussion is over with about death
and טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah huterah betzibur, ending with, although it wasn't
such a heavy death discussion of סוטה Sotah anyway, but all this
issue about closeness to God we end with this מחנה שכינה machaneh
Shechinah and the מחנה צדיקים machaneh tzaddikim and the power over these
bodily functions. I did want to say one thing, it's a very
beautiful idea from the Rav. I did want to say one thing
about the issue about אין בין עולם הזה לימות המשיח, ein bein
Olam Hazeh l'Yemos Hamashiach, especially it also ties into this very last
line we just read. This whole thing that you get resurrected and
then are you resurrected sick or well? Anyway, so רמב"ם Rambam writes,
I think he writes this in his הקדמה לפירוש המשניות. hakdamah le'peirush
hamishnayos. He's very disturbed with how people spend so much of their
religious and mental energies fantasizing and asking questions about ימות המשיח. Yemos
Hamashiach. And they wonder like what's going to happen then, if you
die are you going to get resurrected ninety-five years old with all
of your illnesses or you get resurrected as a young person? If
you married one person and that person died and you married another
person, who's your, who's your... your wife or who's your husband when
you get resurrected so the רמב"ם Rambam just felt this was completely
religiously nonproductive and he wanted to get people to say that this
is a waste of time, we'll worry about it when it happens,
we don't
know, nobody's been there, whatever, we'll worry about it when it happens,
this is not for us to worry about, we have to worry
about our obligations in this world. And therefore, not therefore, but
at the same time רמב"ם Rambam, also writes in his הלכות מלכים
Hilchos Melachim that he says אמרו חז"ל Amru Chazal or he says
אמרו חכמים, Amru Chachamim, I forget the exact phrase, אין בין עולם
הזה לימות המשיח אלא שיעבוד מלכויות. Ein bein olam hazeh liyemos hamashiach
ela shibbud malkhuyos. So he takes what in the גמרא is a
single opinion of שמואל, which is clearly a marginal opinion, and brings
it down as this is the consensus of what חז"ל Chazal have
said, because he wants people not to be focused on this miraculous
messianic times, it'll be a normal time, we'll just have our שיעבוד
מלכויות, Shibbud malkhuyos, we focus on our obligation in this world. The
irony of this is, and Dr. David Berger wrote an article about
this a good 20 years ago or so, is that the effect
of the רמב"ם's Rambam attempt to demystify
messianic times had the exact opposite effect because he said various messianic
movements when they would claim
that they were messianic movements, the challenge would always be, well the
world looks normal, you know it can't be the real messianic movement,
nothing is different, it's all the same, so obviously you're not the
משיח. Mashiach, So the answer was, well just look at the
רמב"ם, Rambam I don't have to do anything miraculous to be the
משיח, the only difference is שיעבוד מלכויות, Shibbud malkhuyos, so that's coming.
So he actually points this
out, he mentions three things, can you figure out? שבתי צבי, Shabbetai
Zevi, right? Can you get the other two? France? No. What? חב"ד,
Chabad, חב"ד Chabad and Reform? No, religious Zionism, that's right, אתחלתא דגאולה.
Aschalta DeGeulah. So right, and he says all of those basically use
the רמב"ם Rambam to say, and certainly religious Zionism, שיעבוד מלכויות, Shibbud
malkhuyos, that's the only difference, so we're there. So anyway, so very
interesting.
חב"ד, Chabad, he wrote that book
on, yeah but this was a little article where he talked about
the effect of the רמב"ם's attempt to demystify, which actually wound up
giving strength to messianic claims. Okay, yes?
Has anyone speculated that רמב"ם might have
adopted philosophy from Sunni Muslims? Oh, I don't know, they don't have
this kind of messianic.
That's interesting, I don't know. Okay, turning the page, we got 15
minutes and the whole עמוד to go. והקטר חלביו, Vehakter chalavav, now
the other thing you do on שבת Shabbos, is you burn the
fat. תניא Tanya on a ברייתא, Braisa אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua, בוא ראה כמה חביבה מצווה בשעתה, Bo re'ei kama chaviva mitzvah
besha'atah, see how dear a mitzvah is in its right time, שהרי
הקטר חלבים ואיברים ופדרים כשרים כל הלילה. Sheharei hekter chalavim ve'evarim upadarim
kesherim kol halaylah. You can burn the fats and the limbs, limbs
isn't appropriate here for the פסח, but okay as a general rule
by an
עולה Olah and the other fats, you can burn them the whole
night, you don't have to burn them the day of the קרבן,
Korban, you can burn them the following night. So if you're bringing
a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on שבת, Shabbos? you could burn the
fats on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can burn them after nightfall.
Why violate שבת? Shabbos. Nevertheless, אין ממתינין להם עד שתחשך, ein mamtinin
lahem ad shetecheshchak, since you're supposed to start on the same day,
you don't wait, you start on the same day even if it's
שבת. Shabbos. Once there's an override, even though this didn't have to
be done, it was part of the הקרבה, Hakravah, the קרבן, Korban,
and you do it on שבת. Shabbos, הרכבתה והבאתה, Harkavatah vahava'atah, you
can carry it and the carrying and the bringing of it, that
you cannot do, that's a even though it's only rabbinic, it could
have been done the day before. So the גמרא says, and one
of the things you can't do is cut off a like a
wart, which is a מום, Mum, and you can't do it even
with your teeth and even with a שינוי, Shinuy, presumably, even though
it's only rabbinic. So the גמרא says ורמינהי, Veramini, I'll ask you
on this, we have a ברייתא Braisa in עירובין Eruvin that says
חותכין יבלת במקדש. Chotchin yabelet bamukdash. Forget the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
for any קרבן Korban that's brought to the מקדש Mikdash on שבת,
Shabbos, you can cut off a wound, like a wart or something
like a hanging
piece of skin that would be a מום, Mum, because it's only
a rabbinic prohibition and we say אין שבות במקדש, ein shvus bamikdash,
we don't worry about rabbinic prohibitions in the מקדש. Mikdash. So the
other things like bringing the קרבן, Korban, we're not in the מקדש,
they were getting the קרבן Korban there, that we accept that we're
not going to allow it even though it's only rabbinic, you should
have done it yesterday, don't carry your קרבן Korban or whatever. But
if it's in the מקדש and it has a מום, Mum, we
actually say that you're allowed to take off the מום Mum on
שבת, Shabbos so why here you're giving this guy a hard time?
So אבל לא במדינה, Aval lo bamedinah, not outside the מקדש. ואם
בכלי, Ve'im bikli, but that's like using your teeth to do it
with a or your hand to do it with like a knife
and a כלי, Kli, a vessel, to do it in a normal
way, כאן וכאן אסור, kan vechan assur, either way it's forbidden. רבי
אלעזר ורבי יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Yose bar Chanina, both
of them have answers and our משנה Mishna says that it's forbidden
סתם. So the גמרא says רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi
Elazar veRabbi Yose bar Chanina, both of them have answers. חד אמר,
Chad amar, one says אידי ואידי ביד, idi ve'idi beyad, our משנה
Mishna and the ברייתא Braisa. are talking about using your hand, clearly
the ברייתא Braisa, is, so why does our משנה Mishna say it's
forbidden and the ברייתא say it's
okay? הא בלחה הא ביבשה, Ha belachah ha beyaveshah, one's talking
about moist and the other's talking about dry. If it's moist and
it's really part of the body, then it's more prohibited. and therefore
you're not allowed to do it. If it's dried and it's really
no longer part of the body, then you're allowed to do it.
Okay, so fine, so you need two criteria to use your hand
and for it to be dried. וחד אמר, vechad amar, the other
one
says, אידי ואידי בלחה. idi veidi belacha. No, they're both talking about
moist. That you're allowed to do it even if it's moist. He's
actually arguing not just an interpretation but in הלכה. ולא קשיא הא
ביד הא בכלי. velo kashya ha beyad ha bekli. When the ברייתא
is clear you can do it with your hand. When our משנה
Mishnah says you can't do it, it's talking about using an actual
vessel, doing it in the normal way. So according to this opinion,
you only need one criteria. If you do it with your hand,
you're allowed to do it even if it's moist and it's more
part of the body. So the גמרא says, ולמאן דאמר הא ביד
הא בכלי, uleman deamar ha beyad ha bekli, according to the one
that says that's the difference, the second opinion, whether you use your
hand or not, but it's allowed even if...
what? If it's dried, what's the problem then? It's really not considered
part of the body.
That's a question. If it's dried, like why is it אסור במדינה
assur bemdina and why is it אסור assur with a כלי? kli?
That's sort of what the גמרא is
going to say. ולמאן דאמר אידי ואידי ביד, uleman deamar idi veidi
beyad, why did you not like the other answer that says that
we're talking both cases using a hand ולא קשיא הא בלחה הא
ביבשה velo kashya ha belacha ha beyavesha and the difference is whether
it's moist or dried, that the ברייתא only allows it if it's
both your hand and dried, dried
up. אמר לך אי הכי יבשה amar lach ee hachi yavesha dried
out, מפרך פריך, mifrach parich, then it's just like crumbling, which the
way תוספות Tosafot reads it is like you said Michael. Then why
is there a problem doing it בכלי? bekli? And then why is
it a problem במדינה? bemdina? If it's dried out, it's not even
anything. Okay, ולמאן דאמר...
so how does he read it then? So if that's the case,
then what does...
then why then it's no issue at all. Then why should it
be a problem with a כלי, why should it be a problem
במדינה, bemdina, it's just crumbling, you're not even doing anything problematic.
But it is a problem.
Not according to the second opinion. Second opinion says if it's dried
up, it's not a problem at all. ולמאן דאמר אידי ואידי ביד
ולא קשיא הא בלחה הא ביבשה, uleman deamar idi veidi beyad velo
kashya ha belacha ha beyavesha, and according to the one that says
they're in both cases it's a hand and you need two things,
a hand and dried out, and that's the ברייתא, מאי טעמא לא
אמר אידי ואידי בלחה ולא קשיא הא ביד הא בכלי? mai taama
lo amar idi veidi belacha velo kashya ha beyad ha bekli? Why
didn't he say the difference is both talking about where it's still
moist and the difference is that the ברייתא allows it with your
hand and the משנה Mishnah prohibits it with a
vessel? אמר לך כלי הקטני התם. amar lach kli haktani hatam. No,
you wouldn't need the משנה Mishnah to tell you not to use
a vessel, that's explicit in the ברייתא. Of course the משנה Mishnah
talks about פסח, the ברייתא talks in general, anyway. אם בכלי כאן
וכאן אסור. im bekli kan vekan assur. So if the ברייתא already
explicitly says you can't use a vessel, the משנה Mishnah when it
says אסור wouldn't be talking about that case which is already explicit
in the ברייתא. Doesn't seem like such a good argument. ואידך, veidach,
the other would say back, הא דקתני כלי הכא, ha daktani kli
hacha, the reason here we have to repeat the idea that don't
use a vessel even though it's clear in the ברייתא, פלוגתא דרבי
אליעזר ורבי יהושע אתא לאשמועינן, pulgata deRabbi Eliezer veRabbi Yehoshua ata leashmienan,
because of the debate, because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says I let
you do things ערב erev you know on שבת Shabbos evening even
if you could have done them the day before. I let you
do certainly דרבננס, derabbanans, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer maybe even lets you
do דאורייתאס, deoraitas, you know, of הכשר מצוה. hechsher mitzvah. So it
doesn't... it's not repetitive, we need to say it in the context
of the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, which is obviously a big obligation
and according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you have license to do
things even on שבת Shabbos? that could have been done even things
that could have been done the day before. Okay, so that just
clarifies that the prohibition of cutting this wart is not necessarily so
prohibited as we thought and our משנה Mishnah is only talking in
a narrower case where it would be prohibited. Let's take a look
at the next issue where we finally get to this debate about
can you do things that could have been done the day before,
can you do them on שבת? אמר רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer,
ומה אם שחיטה, umah im shechita, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, look,
if you do שחיטה shechita of the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, you
can certainly do rabbinic things. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no
you can't and in one of the proofs of רבי אליעזר... Rabbi
Eliezer... of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was, look, on יום טוב Yom
Tov you can cook, but you can't go ahead and chop wood
because you could have done that the day before even though you're
doing it for cooking, or you can't even do דרבננס derabbanans that
you could have done the day before. And רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's
response to that was, cook... you know, cooking on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, that's a רשות, reshus, that doesn't give you
as much license. Cooking... קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, that's a real obligation,
so that gives you more license. So don't prove to me anything
from the fact that we don't allow rabbinic prohibitions that could have
been done the day before for the sake of cooking. Cooking on
יום טוב Yom Tov is not in the same category, is not
really a מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא says, really? What about שמחת
יום טוב? simchat Yom Tov? So let's take a look. רבי יהושע
לטעמיה, Rabbi Yehoshua letaamei, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that cooking on
יום טוב Yom Tov is not such a מצוה mitzvah and doesn't
give some... and I mean...
I'm sorry, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's not such a מצוה
mitzvah and it doesn't give you so much license. רבי יהושע... Rabbi
Yehoshua... רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said... wait, did I get this mixed
up?
Yes. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua thought you could bring a proof from
the prohibition of דרבננס derabbanans for making food. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said back to him, that's only a
רשות. reshus. So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua clearly felt it was comparable
to the קרבן פסח korban Pesach and felt that it was a
מצוה. mitzvah. So that's what the גמרא says. רבי יהושע לטעמיה, Rabbi
Yehoshua letaamei, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua goes according to his reasoning דאמר
שמחת יום טוב נמי מצוה היא. deamar simchat Yom Tov nami mitzvah
hee. Look, שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov is also a מצוה,
mitzvah, and if you can't do דרבננס derabbanans for שמחת יום טוב
simchat Yom Tov that you could have done the day before, you
can't do it for קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. דתניא, detanya, and this
debate of רבי The debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is explicitly also a debate about שמחת יום טוב
Simchas Yom Tov the same way they debated things you could do
for
a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. דתניא בברייתא, Detanya ba-braisa, רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, אין לו לאדם ביום טוב ein lo la-adam be-Yom
Tov אלא אוכל ושותה ela ochel v'shose או יושב ושונה. o yoshev
v'shone. Either on יום טוב Yom Tov you do one or the
other. You spend it with divine pursuit or with physical pleasures. Okay.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, yes, smack it with learning. רבי
יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, חלקהו, chalkeihu, split it. חציו לאכילה וחציו
לבית המדרש. Chetzyo l'achila v'chetzyo l'Beis HaMidrash. Half has to be, half
for ה', God, half for yourself for physical pleasure. So רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua felt a physical שמחת יום טוב, Simchas Yom Tov, not
only an intellectual and spiritual, is always a מצוה. mitzvah. So if
for that מצוה mitzvah we don't allow דרבננס, derabanans, we won't allow
it for קרבן פסח Korban Pesach as well. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer answered back and he said, no, I don't think a physical
שמחת יום טוב Simchas Yom Tov is necessary. You could be מקיים
mikayeim שמחת יום טוב Simchas Yom Tov with a purely spiritual pursuit.
ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. u'shneihem mikra
echad darshu. They both learn from one verse. פסוק אחד אומר, Pasuk
echad omer, עצרת לה' אלקיך, Atzeres l'Hashem Elokecha, that it should be
a holding back for ה' Hashem your God. וכתוב אחד אומר, V'chasuv
echad omer, עצרת יהיה לכם, Atzeres yiheye lachem, it should be an
עצרת Atzeres for you. So רבי אליעזר סבר, Rabbi Eliezer savar, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds, או כולו לה' או כולו לכם. o kulo
l'Hashem o kulo lachem. Either you,
it's one or the other. You either make it a day for
ה' God or a day for you. רבי יהושע סבר Rabbi Yehoshua
savar and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, חלקהו, chalkeihu, split it. חציו
לה' וחציו לכם. Chetzyo l'Hashem v'chetzyo lachem. Half for ה' God and
half for you. I don't know. We will pick up with this
tomorrow. We have to end a minute or two early today because
on Tuesdays we have to clear the room.